Hi again. This is another
farm concept review question.
So we have a 29-year-old female
presented to the ED
with nausea, vomiting,
dizziness, and
ringing in the ears.
Past medical history
reveals major depression,
iron deficiency, anemia,
and migraine headaches.
Vital signs reveal
the temperature of 98,
blood pressure is a
little low, heart rate
is elevated, respiratory
rate is high.
Physical exam
revealed rapid, deep
breathing, but no
other abnormalities.
While waiting for
her blood to be
drawn for these
tests, the patient
produces a small
volume of black emesis.
Significant lab findings
included that her
chloride was low, her
bicarbonate was low, creatinine
was elevated which is
the most appropriate
treatment so we're dealing
with an overdose we're
looking at the respiratory
rate being high and
she has rapid deep
breathing okay and then
when we're looking at
the layer values we're
also concerned with the
imbalance of the fact
that both chloride and
bicarbonate are low.
So what does she overdose
on? Because that's what
we're looking for and what it
looks like is in the answers
is some kind of antidote.
So let's go through A.
Ciprohiptidine is a serotonin
blocker. It also has histamine,
some dopamine,
some alpha, and some
muscarinic block. They can
use it for allergies. They
can use it, maybe it has
some anti-emetic potential,
but with those adverse
effects coming from those
blockades, it's mainly
utilized as a antidote
for serotonin syndrome.
Why I think it's not serotonin
syndrome, even though
she has major depressive
disorder and she could
be taking sertraline is
that her temperature is not
elevated also I would
expect her blood pressure to
be high her heart rate
is high but um that's not
given here with her
presentation the other thing I
would be concerned with is
the fact that with serotonin
syndrome she would
probably be having seizures
she would be myoclonic so
I can safely say that this
is probably not a serotonin
syndrome presentation.
D-ferrooxamine, okay, so
the iron deficiency anemia.
The only thing that I
might say is that with iron
toxicity, she may get this
gastritis that's hemorrhagic.
So she could have, you
know, vomited blood.
She might be somewhat you
know dizzy but the chloride
and bicarbonate and creatinine
most likely would not
be affected with the
ferrooxamine okay naloxone again
this is a no because with
naloxone the respiratory rate
would probably be more like
eight and in addition blood
pressure okay is low so with
the heart rate. We would
also have a patient who is
unconscious. We would have
a patient that has meiosis.
So that's not the case.
N-acetylcysteine or NAC will
donate sulfhydryl groups
in patients that have
overdosed N-acetaminophen.
Acetaminophen, again, the
issue is the liver that
you want to create more
sulfhydro groups for GSH to
neutralize the NAP-QI because
NAP-QI is what's binding
to the liver to cause
central lobular necrosis.
With Tylenol toxicity, there
may be some nausea, vomiting,
maybe some loss of appetite.
If anything in her labs, she
may have a change in her PT,
INR and most likely you
would probably get something
going on with the liver
function test. So I'm
going to probably say it's
not a Tylenol toxicity.
Sodium bicarbonate. So again
makes sense for a couple
of reasons. Number one,
the respiratory rate. Okay.
So number one, When you're
overdosing on aspirin,
you're going to
have an increase in
respiratory rate
because your body is
trying to blow off
the carbon dioxide.
So that's alkalosis.
And then as time goes
on, you go into acidosis.
That has to do
with the uncoupling
of oxidative phosphorylation.
The other thing that stands
out that I didn't bring
up is hopefully the ringing
of the years. and that's
an early presentation of
a aspirin toxicity. So
with aspirin toxicity
there's no specific antidote.
Aspirin is acetic, salicylic
acid. You want to make
sure you increase ion trapping.
The way you do that is
to give something that is
going to ionize an acetic
compound and that's sodium
bicarb. So by doing that
you're going to prevent
reabsorption from the kidney
and your aspirin is going
to be excreted nicely.
So E is the best answer.
This is an aspirin overdose.
So neurologically,
tinnitus and dizziness,
that's the ringing of the ears.
Initially, it's alkalosis.
In the GI, you're
losing prostaglandin, so
you're going to get
GI irritation, maybe
some bloody emesis with
uric acid uric acid
competes for excretion
with salicylic acid
salicylic acid gets
excreted but uric acid does
get recovered and that
means somebody with gout
is going to have more
of a problem in that
pathway and I've showed
you before it starts with
arachnidonic acid, and
then it goes down the
cyclooxygenase and then
the lipooxygenase pathway.
In those patients that
are allergic to aspirin,
the whole action is shifting
towards leukotrienes.
That's why they're
getting bronchospasm,
itchiness, things of that
nature. If you're allergic
to aspirin, you're going
to be allergic to NSAIDs.
So avoid NSAIDs if you're
allergic to aspirin.
And then in the kidney,
aspirin and NSAIDs are
going to vasoconstrict in
the afferent arteriole.
And then if you're using
aspirin, it's going to
increase bleeding time.
So if you're going for
a surgical procedure,
they often recommend in
the days before the
procedure you go off aspirin.
And remember, the big thing
with aspirin is thromboxane
because it's an irreversible
acetylation of ***.
With NSAIDs, it's reversible.
That's why we don't
have NSAIDs being platelet
aggregator inhibitors.
Okay, so these are the effects.
Pain relief,
anti-inflammatory,
and antipyretic.
To be honest, we
use more NSAIDs now.
The other thing is we're
talking about Tylenol. Tylenol
can do the analgesia and
the antipyretic, but it
has no effects on inflammation
or antiplatelet action.
Remember, acetaminophen has
a weak psychooxygenase block.
And then Rye's
syndrome means we don't
give these drugs to
pediatric patients.
Zero order elimination
means the more
I give, I'm not
changing elimination.
And that can put your patient
at a dangerous toxicity.
This happens with phenytoin,
with ethanol, and with aspirin.
And then the antidote is to
alkanolize the urine. Thank
you all for your attention,
and I'll see you soon.